When I was a kid,
عندما كنت طفلاً،
I experienced something so powerful,
جربت شيئاً مؤثراً جداً،
I spent the rest of my life searching for it,
قضيت بقية حياتي أبحث عنه،
and in all the wrong places.
وفي كل الأماكن الخطأ.
What I experienced wasn't virtual reality.
ما جربته لم يكن الواقع الإفتراضي.
It was music.
بل كانت الموسيقى.
And this is where the story begins.
و هنا حيث تبدأ القصة.
That's me,
هأنذا،
listening to the Beatles' "White Album."
أستمع إلى فرقة البيتلز( الألبوم الأبيض).
And the look on my face is the feeling
و النظرة البادية على وجهي هي الإحساس
that I've been searching for ever since.
الذي ظللت أبحث عنه منذ ذلك الحين.
Music goes straight to the emotional vein,
تتجه الموسيقى مباشرة إلى وريد المشاعر،
into your bloodstream
في مجرى دمك
and right into your heart.
و مباشرةً إبى قلبك.
It deepens every experience.
إنها تُعَمِّقُ كل التجارب.
Fellas?
أصحاب؟
(Music)
(موسيقى)
This is the amazing McKenzie Stubbert
هؤلاء الرائعون هم (ماكنزي ستبرت)
and Joshua Roman.
و (جوشوا رومان)
Music --
موسيقى --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Yeah.
نعم.
Music makes everything have more emotional resonance.
تعطي الموسيقى مزيداً من الرنين العاطفي لكل شيء.
Let's see how it does for this talk.
لنرى تأثيرها على هذا الحديث.
The right piece of music at the right time fuses with us
الموسيقى المناسبة في الوقت المناسب تذوب فينا
on a cellular level.
على مستوى الخلايا.
When I hear that one song
عندما أسمع تحديداً هذه الأغنية
from that one summer
في ذلك الصيف
with that one girl,
مع تلك الفتاة،
I'm instantly transported back there again.
أنتقل لحظياً إلى هناك مرة أخرى.
Hey, Stacey.
مرحبا (ستيسي).
Here's a part of the story, though, where I got a little greedy.
إليكم فصلاً من القصة، عندما أصبحت طماعاً بعض الشيء.
I thought if I added more layers on top of the music,
ظننت أنني لو أضفت عدة طبقات عند بداية الموسيقى،
I could make the feelings even more powerful.
سأتمكن من جعل الإحساس أقوى.
So I got into directing music videos.
لذا بدأت في إخراج فيديوهات موسيقية.
This is what they looked like.
وهذا هو ما بدوا عليه.
That's my brother, Jeff.
هذا أخي (جيف).
Sorry about this, Jeff.
آسف على هذا (جيف).
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here's me, just so we're even.
وهأنذا، وبذلك نكون قد تعادلنا.
Incredible moves.
حركات رهيبة.
Should've been a dancer.
كان علي أن أصبح راقصاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
These experiments grew,
نَضُجَتْ هذه التجارب،
and in time, started to look more like this.
ومع الوقت، بدأت تبدو أكثر كهذه.
In both, I'm searching for the same thing, though,
في التجربتين، رغم أنني أبحث عن نفس الشئ،
to capture that lightning in a bottle.
وهو أن أفعل المستحيل.
Except, I'm not.
إلا أنني لم أستطع.
Adding moving pictures over the music added narrative dimension, yes,
إضافة صور متحركة للموسيقى، إضافة بعد قصصي لها، نعم،
but never quite equated the power
لكن، هذا لم يعادل أبداً القوة
that just raw music had for me on its own.
التي تكمن في الموسيقي البحتة ذاتها.
This is not a great thing to realize when you've devoted your life
وهذا ليس شيئاً جيداً استنتاجه عندما تكون قد وهبت حياتك
and professional career to becoming a music video director.
ومسيرتك المهنية لتكون مُخرج فيديوهات موسيقية.
I kept asking myself, did I take the wrong path?
ظللت أسأل نفسي، هل سلكت الطريق الخاطئ؟
So I started thinking: if I could involve you, the audience, more,
ولذا بدأت أفكر: إذا كان بإمكاني أن أُشرِكَكُم أنتم، والمستمعين، وآخرين،
I might be able to make you feel something more as well.
ربما تمكنت من جعلكم تشعرون بما هو أقوى أيضاً.
So Aaron Koblin and I began auditioning new technologies
ولذا، فقد بدأت و (أرون كوبلين) نبحث عن تقنيات جديدة
that could put more of you inside of the work,
حيث تُمَكِّنكم من المشاركة فيما نصنع،
like your childhood home in "The Wilderness Downtown,"
مثل بيت طفولتك، كما في أغنية (صحراء وسط البلد)،
your hand-drawn portraits, in "The Johnny Cash Project,"
أو رسمتك التي رسمتها لـ(مشروع جوني كاش)،
and your interactive dreams
وكل أحلامك التفاعلية
in "3 Dreams of Black."
في (3 أحلام للأسْوَدْ).
We were pushing beyond the screen,
كنا نبحث فيما وراء الشاشة،
trying to connect more deeply
في محاولة للتواصل تواصلاً أعمق
to people's hearts and imaginations.
بقلوب الناس وخيالهم.
But it wasn't quite enough.
لكن هذا لم يكن كافياً.
It still didn't have the raw experiential power of pure music for me.
لم نصل بعد للقوة الخام للموسيقى البحتة في رأيي.
So I started chasing a new technology
ولهذا بدأت بالبحث عن تقنية جديدة
that I only had read about in science fiction.
التي قرأت عنها فقط في الخيال العلمي.
And after years of searching, I found a prototype.
وبعد سنوات من البحث، وجدت نموذج بدائي.
It was a project from Nonny de la Peña in Mark Bolas's lab in USC.
وهو مشروع من (نوني دو لابينيا) في معمل (مارك بولاس) بجامعة جنوب كاليفورنيا.
And when I tried it, I knew I'd found it.
وعندما جربته، علمت أنني وجدت ما أبحث عنه.
I could taste the lightning.
استطعت أن أصل للمستحيل.
It was called virtual reality.
كان اسمه الواقع الإفتراضي.
This was it five years ago when I ran into it.
هذا كان منذ خمس سنوات عندما توصلت إليه.
This is what it looks like now.
هذا هو ما يبدو عليه الآن.
I quickly started building things in this new medium,
بدأت سريعاً في صناعة أشياء جديدة في ذلك الوسط الجديد،
and through that process we realized something:
وخلال ذلك تبين لنا شئ ما:
that VR is going to play an incredibly important role
أن الواقع الإفتراضي سيلعب دوراً هاماً
in the history of mediums.
في تاريخ كل الوسائط.
In fact, it's going to be the last one.
في الواقع، سيكون الأخير.
I mean this because it's the first medium that actually makes the jump
أعني هذا لأنه الوسط الأول الذي صنع القفزة
from our internalization of an author's expression
من أخذ خبرة أحد المؤلفين
of an experience,
عن تجربة ما،
to our experiencing it firsthand.
إلى تجربتنا لذلك الشيءفي البداية.
You look confused. I'll explain. Don't worry.
تبدو عليكم الحيرة. سأشرح هذا. لا تقلقوا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If we go back to the origins of mediums,
إذا عدنا للوراء إلي أصول كل الوسائط،
by all best guesses,
وبالتخمين الجيد،
it starts around a fire, with a good story.
تبدأ الحكاية بجلوسنا حول النار، لنحكي قصة جميلة.
Our clan leader is telling us
زعيم قبيلتنا يخبرنا
about how he hunted the woolly mammoth on the tundra that day.
عن كيفية اصطياده للماموث في السهل في ذلك اليوم.
We hear his words
نستمع إلي كلماته
and translate them into our own internal truths.
ونترجمها بما يتوافق مع ما نعرفه بداخلنا.
The same thing happens
نفس الشئ يحصل
when we look at the cave painting version of the story,
عندما ننظر إلي رسمة كهف عن تلك القصة،
the book about the mammoth hunt,
أو نقرأ كتابا عن اصطياد الماموث،
the play,
أو نراه في مسرحية،
the radio broadcast,
أو نسمعه في الإذاعة،
the television show
أو في عرض تليفزيوني
or the movie.
أو في فيلم.
All of these mediums require what we call "suspension of disbelief,"
كل هذه الوسائط تتطَلَب منا ما نسميه "تعطيل الشك،"
because there's a translation gap between the reality of the story
لأن هناك فجوة نقل بين واقع القصة
and our consciousness interpreting the story
ووعينا الذي يفسر القصة
into our reality.
ويحولها لواقعنا الخاص بنا.
I'm using the word "consciousness" as a feeling of reality that we get
أستخدم كلمة "وعي" هنا بمعني إحساسنا بالواقع الذي يتكون
from our senses experiencing the world around us.
من تجاربنا مع عالمنا المحيط بنا.
Virtual reality bridges that gap.
يَسُدُّ الواقع الإفتراضي تلك الفجوة.
Now, you are on the tundra hunting with the clan leader.
الآن، تخيلوا أنكم في السهل تصطادون مع زعيم القبيلة.
Or you are the clan leader.
أو أنك أنت نفسك زعيم القبيلة.
Or maybe you're even the woolly mammoth.
أو بإمكانك حتي أن تكون الماموث ذا الصوف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So here's what special about VR.
إليكم ما يهم عن الواقع الإفتراضي.
In all other mediums,
في كل الوسائط الأخري،
your consciousness interprets the medium.
يفسر وعيك البيئة من حولك.
In VR, your consciousness is the medium.
في الواقع الإفتراضي، وعيك هو نفسه البيئة.
So the potential for VR is enormous.
ولذا فإن إمكانيات الواقع الإفتراضي هائلة.
But where are we now?
لكن أين نحن الآن؟
What is the current state of the art?
ما هو الوضع الحالي للفن؟
Well,
حسناً،
we are here.
نحن هنا.
We are the equivalent of year one of cinema.
كما لو كنا في السنة الأولى للسينما.
This is the Lumière Brothers film
هذا هو فيلم (الإخوان لوميير)
that allegedly sent a theater full of people running for their lives
الذَين جعل الناس في مسرح ممتلئ يهربون لإنقاذ حياتهم
as they thought a train was coming toward them.
لأنهم ظَنُّوا أن هناك قطاراً قادماً ناحيتهم.
Similar to this early stage of this medium,
ومُشابِه لتلك المرحلة البدائية من الوسائط،
in VR, we also have to move past the spectacle
في الواقع الإفتراضي، يجب علينا أيضاً أن نتجاوز العرض
and into the storytelling.
وننتقل إلي حكاية القصة.
It took this medium decades
تطلب هذا عقوداً من الزمن
to figure out its preferred language of storytelling,
للتوصل إلي الطريقة الأمثل لحكاية القصة،
in the form of a feature film.
وذلك من خلال فيلم مُصَوَّر.
In VR today, we're more learning grammar
في الواقع الإفتراضي اليوم، نتعلم قواعد الكتابة أكثر
than writing language.
مما نكتب.
We've made 15 films in the last year at our VR company, Vrse,
لقد صنعنا 15 فيلماً في العام الماضي في شركتنا الإفتراضية، (فرسي)،
and we've learned a few things.
وتعلمنا أشياء قليلة.
We found that we have a unique, direct path into your senses,
حيث وجدنا أن لدينا طريقاً مباشراً وفريداً نصل به لحواسِكم،
your emotions, even your body.
مشاعركم، وحتي أجسادكم.
So let me show you some things.
لذا دعوني أريكم بعض الأشياء.
For the purpose of this demo,
من أجل هذا العرض،
we're going to take every direction that you could possibly look,
سنأخذ في الحسبان كل اتجاه من المحتمل أن تنظروا إليه،
and stretch it into this giant rectangle.
ونَبْسُطُهُ في هذا المستطيل الضخم.
OK, here we go.
حسناً، ها نحن ذا.
So, first: camera movement is tricky in VR.
أولاً: حركة الكاميرا مخادعة في الواقع الإفتراضي.
Done wrong, it can actually make you sick.
إذا سارت بشكل خاطئ، فقد تشْعِرَكَمْ بالدُوار.
We found if you move the camera at a constant speed in a straight line,
وجدنا أنه لو حركتم الكاميرا بسرعة ثابتة في خط مستقيم،
you can actually get away with it, though.
ستستطيعون فعلاً أن تصنعوا شيئاً رائعاً.
The first day in film school,
في أول يوم في مدرسة الفيلم،
they told me you have to learn every single rule
أخبروني أن عليّ أن أتعلم كل القواعد
before you can break one.
لكي لا أكسر أي منها.
We have not learned every single rule.
ولكننا لم نتعلم كل القواعد.
We've barely learned any at all,
بالكاد تعلمنا إحداها،
but we're already trying to break them
ولكننا كنا نحاول بالفعل كسرها
to see what kind of creative things we can accomplish.
لنرى ما الأشياء الإبداعية التي بإمكاننا تحقيقها.
In this shot here, where we're moving up off the ground, I added acceleration.
في هذه اللقطة هنا، حيث نتحرك قُبالة الأرض، قمت بتسريعها.
I did that because I wanted to give you a physical sensation
فعلت ذلك لأني أردت أن يصلكم الإحساس الفعلي
of moving up off the ground.
بالحركة علي الأرض.
In VR, I can give that to you.
في الواقع الإفتراضي، أستطيع أن أفعل ذلك.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Not surprisingly, music matters a lot in this medium as well.
وبطبيعة الحال، الموسيقى مهمة جداً في هذا الوسط أيضاً.
It guides us how to feel.
لأنها توجه مشاعرنا.
In this project we made with the New York Times, Zach Richter
في هذا المشروع الذي صنعناه مع (النيويورك تايمز) و(زاك ريشتر)
and our friend, JR,
وصديقنا (ج ر)،
we take you up in a helicopter,
نأخذكم عالياً داخل هيلكوبتر،
and even though you're flying 2,000 feet above Manhattan,
وعلي الرغم من أنكم تُحَلِّقون الآن علي إرتفاع 2000 قدم فوق منهاتن،
you don't feel afraid.
فأنتم لا تشعرون بالخوف.
You feel triumphant for JR's character.
بل تشعرون بزهو انتصار شخصية (ج ر).
The music guides you there.
وجهتكم الموسيقى لذلك.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Contrary to popular belief,
علي النقيض من المُعتَقَد المشهور،
there is composition in virtual reality,
هناك أسلوب للتأليف في الواقع للإفتراضي،
but it's completely different than in film,
لكنه مختلف تماماً عن أسلوب الأفلام،
where you have a rectangular frame.
حيث لديك صورة مستطيلة الشكل.
Composition is now where your consciousness exists
أسلوب التأليف مُستوحى من وعيك الآن
and how the world moves around you.
وكيفية حركة العالم من حولك.
In this film, "Waves of Grace," which was a collaboration between Vrse,
في هذا الفيلم، (أمواج المجد) والذي كان بالتعاون مع شركة (فرسي)،
the United Nations, Gabo Arora, and Imraan Ismail,
الأمم المتحدة، (جابو أرورا)، و(عمران إسماعيل)،
we also see the changing role of the close-up in virtual reality.
رأينا نحن أيضاً الدور المُتَغير للإقتراب من الواقع الإفتراضي.
A close-up in VR means you're actually close up to someone.
الإقتراب في الواقع الإفتراضي يعني إقترابك الفعلي من أحد ما.
It brings that character inside of your personal space,
إقتراب يجلب شخصيته داخل نطاقك الشخصي،
a space that we'd usually reserve for the people that we love.
النطاق الذي نحتفظ به عادة للناس الذين نحبهم.
And you feel an emotional closeness to the character
وتشعر بقرب عاطفي للشخصية
because of what you feel to be a physical closeness.
لأنك تشعر بِقٌربهم الجسدي.
Directing VR is not like directing for the rectangle.
يختلف الإخراج في الواقع الإفتراضي عن الإخراج للشاشة المستطيلة.
It's more of a choreography of the viewer's attention.
فهو أكثر شبهاً بالرقصة التي تجلب انتباه المشاهد.
One tool we can use to guide your attention
هناك أداة نستخدمها لتوجيه إنتباهكم
is called "spatialized sound."
نُسَميها " الصوت المكاني."
I can put a sound anywhere in front of you, to left or right,
حيث بإمكاني وضع الصوت في أي مكان أمامكم، علي يساركم أو يمينكم،
even behind you,
وحتي ورائكم،
and when you turn your head, the sound will rotate accordingly.
وعندما تستديرون سيدور الصوت تبعاً لحركتكم.
So I can use that to direct your attention to where I want you to see.
وبهذا أستطيع توجيه إهتمامكم إلي حيث أريدكم أن تنظروا.
Next time you hear someone singing over your shoulder,
في المرة القادمة حين تسمعون أحداً يُغني قُربَ أكتافكم،
it might be Bono.
فلربما يكون هو (بونو).
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
VR makes us feel like we are part of something.
يجعلنا الواقع الإفتراضي نشعر كما لو أننا جزء من شي ما.
For most of human history, we lived in small family units.
غالباً علي مر التاريخ البشري، عشنا في عائلات صغيرة.
We started in caves,
بِدءاً من الكهوف،
then moved to clans and tribes, then villages and towns,
وانتقالاً إلي العشيرة والقبيلة، ثم إلي القُري والمدن،
and now we're all global citizens.
والآن نحن جميعاً مواطنون عالميون.
But I believe that we are still hardwired to care the most
ولكني أعتقد أننا مانزال نربط معظم اهتمامنا
about the things that are local to us.
بالأشياء المحلية القريبة منا.
And VR makes anywhere and anyone feel local.
والواقع الإفتراضي يجعل أي مكان وأي شخص مألوفاً لك.
That's why it works as an empathy machine.
وهذا هو سبب كونه يعمل كآلة للتعاطف.
Our film "Clouds Over Sidra" takes you to a Syrian refugee camp,
يأخذكم فيلمنا (غيوم فوق سيدرا) إلي مخيم للآجئين السوريين،
and instead of watching a story about people over there,
وبدلاً عن مشاهدة قصة عن حياة الناس هناك،
it's now a story about us here.
جعلناها قصة عنا نحن هنا.
But where do we go from here?
لكن أين ذهبنا نحن من هنا؟
The tricky thing is that with all previous mediums,
الخدعة مع كل الوسائط السابقة،
the format is fixed at its birth.
أن طريقة عملها ثابتة منذ صُنِعَت.
Film has been a sequence of rectangles,
الفيلم هو عبارة عن صور مستطيلة متلاحقة،
from Muybridge and his horses to now.
بدءاً ب(مويبريدج) وهو رائد في الصور المتحركة وأحصنته وحتي الآن.
The format has never changed.
الأسلوب لم يتغير أبداً.
But VR as a format, as a medium,
لكن أسلوب الواقع الإفتراضي، كوسط،
isn't complete yet.
لم يكتمل بعد.
It's not using physical celluloid or paper or TV signals.
فهو لا يحتاج شريطا سينمائيا أو ورقة أو إشارة من التلفاز.
It actually employs what we use to make sense of the world.
في الواقع فهو يُوَظِّف ما نستطيع استخدامه لإعطاء معنى للعالم.
We're using your senses as the paints on the canvas,
نحن نستخدم حواسكم كألوان للوحة زيتية،
but only two right now.
لكن اثنين فقط حتي الآن.
Eventually, we can see if we will have all of our human senses employed,
في النهاية، سنري إن كانت كل حواسنا البشرية قد تم تَوظِفها،
and we will have agency to live the story in any path we choose.
وستكون لدينا القوة لنعيش قصة أي طريق نختاره.
And we call it virtual reality right now,
نحن نسميه الواقع الإفتراضي حالياً،
but what happens when we move past simulated realities?
لكن ما الذي سيحدث عندما نتجاوز تقليد الواقع؟
What do we call it then?
ماذا سنُسَميه حينئذ؟
What if instead of verbally telling you about a dream,
ماذا لو أننا بدلاً من الحكاية الشفهية عن حلم،
I could let you live inside that dream?
استطعنا أن نجعلكم تعيشون فيه؟
What if instead of just experiencing visiting some reality on Earth,
ماذا لو عِوضا عن الإكتفاء بزيارة بعض الأماكن علي الأرض،
you could surf gravitational waves on the edge of a black hole,
أن يكون باستطاعتك التزلج علي موجات الجاذبية علي حافة الثقب الأسود،
or create galaxies from scratch,
أو أن تُنشئ مجرة من البداية،
or communicate with each other not using words
أو أن نتواصل مع بعضنا البعض دون استخدام كلمات
but using our raw thoughts?
لكن بتفكيرنا المُجَرَد؟
That's not a virtual reality anymore.
لم يعد هذا واقعاً إفتراضياً بعد الآن.
And honestly I don't know what that's called.
وبكل صراحة أنا لا أدري ماذا يمكن أن نُسَميه.
But I hope you see where we're going.
لكن أتمني أن الأمور قد اتضح لكم مسارها.
But here I am, intellectualizing a medium I'm saying is experiential.
لكن هأنذا، أُمَجِّد في وسط مازال تجريبياً.
So let's experience it.
لذا هيا بنا نجربنه.
In your hands, you hopefully hold a piece of cardboard.
في أيديكم الأن كما آمل، تمسكون بورقة كرتونية.
Let's open the flap.
افتحوا الورقة المطوية.
Tap on the power button to unlock the phone.
واضغطوا علي زر التشغيل لفتح الهاتف.
For the people watching at home,
للناس الذين يشاهدون ذلك في المنزل،
we're going to put up a card right now
سنعرض البطاقة لكم الآن
to show you how to download this experience on your phone yourself,
لنُريكم كيفية تحميلها علي هواتفكم،
and even get a Google cardboard of your own to try it with.
ستحصلون حتى علي ورقة كرتونية من (جوجل) لتجربوها بأنفسكم.
We played in cardboard boxes as kids,
لقد لعبنا بعُلَب الورق المقوى في طفولتنا،
and as adults, I'm hoping we can all find a little bit of that lightning
وكبالغين، أتمني أن نستطيع إيجاد قليل من الإلهام
by sticking our head in one again.
من خلال وضع رؤوسنا بداخلها مرة أخري.
You're about to participate
أنتم علي وشك المشاركة
in the largest collective VR viewing in history.
في أضخم درس جماعي عن الواقع الإفتراضي في التاريخ.
And in that classic old-timey style of yesteryear,
وبهذه الطريقة التقليدية للسنوات الماضية،
we're all going to watch something
كلنا سنشاهد شيئاً ما
at the exact same time, together.
في نفس الوقت، معاً.
Let's hope it works.
لنأمل أن تعمل.
What's the countdown look like? I can't see.
لنعد تنازلياً، أنا لا أستطيع الرؤية.
Audience: ...15, 14, 13, 12, 11, 10, 9,
الجمهور:... 15، 14، 13، 12، 11، 10، 9،
8, 7, 6, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1
8، 7، 6، 5، 4، 3، 2، 1
(Birds singing)
(طيور تغني)
(Train engine)
(محرك قطار)
Audience: (Shreiks)
الجمهور: (صرخات)
(Video) JR: Let me tell you
(فيديو) ج ر: دعوني أخبركم
how I shot the cover of the New York Times Magazine,
كيف التقطت صورة غلاف مجلة (نيويورك تايمز)،
"Walking New York."
لعدد (نيويورك تسير).
I just got strapped on outside the helicopter,
تم ربطي من خاصرتي إلي طائرة هليكوبتر،
and I had to be perfectly vertical so I could grab it.
وكنت في وضع عمودي لكي أتمكن من الإمساك بها.
And when I was perfectly above --
وعندما كنت مباشرة فوق --
you know, with the wind, we had to redo it a few times --
لعلكم تعلمون، بسبب الرياح، نُضطَر لتكرار الأمرعدة مرات --
then I kept shooting.
وظللت ألتقط صوراً.
(Video) Woman's voice: Dear Lord,
(فيديو) صوت إمرأة: يإ إلهي،
protect us from evil,
احمنا من الشرور،
for you are the Lord,
فأنت الله،
the light.
أنت النور.
You who gave us life took it away.
يامن تُحيينا وتُميتنا.
Let your will be done.
يامن تقول للشيء كن فيكون.
Please bring peace to the many who have lost loved ones.
أنعِم بالسلام علي الكثيرين ممن فقدوا أحباءهم.
Help us to live again.
ساعدهم ليستطيعوا إكمال حياتهم.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Video) (Children's voices)
(فيديو) (أصوات أطفال)
Child's voice: There are more kids in Zaatari than adults right now.
صوت طفل: هناك العديد من الأطفال في مخيم الزعتري أصبحوا كباراً الآن.
Sometimes I think
أحيانا أفكر
we are the ones in charge.
أننا المسؤولون.
Chris Milk: How was it?
كريس مايك: كيف كان ذلك؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
That was a cheap way of getting you to do a standing ovation.
كانت تلك طريقة رخيصة لأجعلكم تقفون مصفقين.
I just made you all stand. I knew you'd applaud at the end.
أنا فقط جعلتكم تقفون جميعاً. عرفت أنكم ستصفقون في النهاية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I believe that everyone on Earth needs to experience
أؤمن بأن الجميع علي الأرض يحتاجون لتجربة
what you just experienced.
ما اختبرناه نحن الآن.
That way we can collectively start to shape this,
بهذه الطريقة نستطيع جميعاً أن نبدأ بتشكيل هذا،
not as a tech platform
ليس كمنصة تقنية
but as a humanity platform.
لكن كمنصة إنسانية.
And to that end, in November of last year,
وإلي هذه النهاية، في نوفمبر من العام الماضي،
the New York Times and Vrse made a VR project called "The Displaced."
نيويورك تايمز وشركة فرسي صنعوا مشروعا أسموه "النازحون".
It launched with one million Google Cardboards
تم إطلاقة بواسطة مليون بطاقة من (جوجل)
sent out to every Sunday subscriber with their newspaper.
أُرسِلَت لكل مشترك في جريدة صانداي مع نسختهم.
But a funny thing happened that Sunday morning.
لكن شئ مضحك حدث في صبيحة يوم الأحد.
A lot of people got them
الكثيرون ممن حصلوا عليها
that were not the intended recipients on the mailing label.
لم يكونوا هم المستلمين المسجَلين في البريد.
And we started seeing this all over Instagram.
ورأينا هذا في كل مكان علي الإنستجرام.
Look familiar?
يبدو أمراً مألوفاً ؟
Music led me on a path
الموسيقى قادتني إلى طريق
of searching for what seemed like the unattainable
البحث عن ما بدا صعب المنال
for a very long time.
لوقتٍ طويلٍ للغاية.
Now, millions of kids just had the same formative experience
الآن، ملايين الأطفال اختبروا نفس التجربة
in their childhood
في طفولتهم
that I had in mine.
كالتي عشتها.
Only I think this one
وأظن أن هذه فقط
surpasses it.
تفوق ما عِشتُه.
Let's see
لنترَقَب
where this
إلي أين
leads them.
سيقودهم ذلك.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)